Today I'm on a journey through Devon.
Starting here in the waters near Thurleston and heading all the way east to Tiverton.
My travelling will take me from Thurleston to Plympton, where I'll meet a man who bought his own zoo.
At Calstock, I'll take a trip down the River Tamar, to see a working water mill at St Dominick.
Finally, at Tiverton, I'll be saddling up and trying my hand at an ancient marshal art.
Along the way, I'll be taking a look back at the best of the BBC's rural programmes from this part of the UK.
Devon is a captivating mix of high moors, historic town, wind-blown estuaries and coastal grandeur.
It contains the two National Parks of Exmoor and Dartmoor.
It is the only county in England to have two separate coastlines - the Bristol Channel in the north and the English Channel to the south.
It's on the south-west coast where my travels begin today.
Swimming here is a real treat.
Such a great way to get the day started.
But in these waters, I've been told, I could be just above a shipwreck.
The entire coast of the British Isles is a ship graveyard.
Vessels from centuries of sailing are strewn across the sea floor.
South Devon's coast is no exception.
Scattered along its entire lengths are dozens of shipwrecks, pulverised and then hidden by the sea.
Somewhere below me lies the remains of the Louis Sheid, a Belgium steamer that sunk in 1939, but before I explore the wreck I've got to get kitted out.
I've teamed up with dive instructor Kieran Hatton, who is going to teach me how to snorkel in open water.
So, I've been in, and it's absolutely freezing.
Is the weather conducive for snorkelling today?
For sure.
We are really, really lucky today with a light offshore breeze and dead flat sea conditions.
We can see from the boat that the water's nice and clear, really the pick of the year, so far.
Is this one of the best areas to snorkel in across this coast?
Well, marine life wise it is very diverse.
As a coastline it is a jagged changing coastline, which provides a lot of environment for marine life to grow on, but also I'm interested in the history, the shipwrecks, the Louis Sheid that we have got off the rocks here, the story behind how they got there, why they got there, what they were doing before they got there.
So when we snorkel above the Louis Sheid, what are we going to see?
We are going to jump on the main body of the wreck, over what would be the engine room, the boiler.
They are three really big obvious reference points.
They are standing about four metres proud of the seabed.
This being early in the season, is a great time, the kelp has not grown really tall, so we will see the main body of the wreck.
The best bit is if you look for stuff this big, you won't miss anything in the sea if you swim around looking for your big...
I'm not going to see any killer whales?
No man-eating things, but if we're really lucky we could get big basking sharks, come along the coast here.
They are filter feeders, they swim along the surface.
Their fin and the tip of their nose, giving the tell-tale as to where they are.
SINGS "Jaws" THEME TUNE Same family.
Not man-eaters, though?
No.
So, we'll be OK?
It may just look like a lot of seaweed, but when you delve a little deeper, the remains of the Louis Sheid become apparent.
The engine room... ..and the hull are clearly visible, but if you didn't know it was here, there's a really good chance you could swim right over it.
Why was it wrecked here?
It's very unfortunate.
She went to the aid of a Dutch steam ship that had been torpedoed out in the channel and she collected the surviving crew from that ship.
Then to protect herself, was running for the safety of the shoreline of the UK, but due to blackout conditions, all of the village lights were blacked out, there were no lighthouses and in a heavy storm, and rain, she narrowly missed the headland and ran straight up the rocks where we are now.
Everyone was taken off, survived?
Yeah, everybody on board the Louis Sheid survived.
Incredible.
The Louis Sheid has been lying here for over 70 years.
Marine life now covers every inch of her.
It's hard to imagine that once she was an ocean-going ship.
What an amazing experience!
Snorkelling with Kieran has given me such an incredible appreciation of Devon from the sea, but now it's time to take my journey inland.
Thurleston is just one of the many wonderful beaches on this stretch of coast.
Just a few miles away is Carlyon Bay, a beach where all is not what it seems.
You are probably not going to find another beach like this in the world.
Glynda Easterbrook has been examining its extraordinary make-up.
If I brought my children down on to this beach I wouldn't give this stuff a second thought.
It looks like sand.
It does, doesn't it.
But in this bottle, I have some sand that I collected from another beach somewhere else in Cornwall.
If you look at it closely, you can see how different it is.
This is very soft, almost smooth.
This is hard and granular.
It's nice and soft because it has shell-y fragments in it.
This is nearly all quartz.
This is no average beach.
All other Cornish beaches are a mixture of eroded granite and crushed sea shells, but this one at Carlyon Bay is mostly made of quartz.
This is a typical Cornish granite.
Granite is made of three main minerals - quartz, which is this grey glassy stuff here.
It's got great big white crystals of a mineral that we call feldspar and it's got some little black shiny grains which is mica.
The quartz and the mica ended up on the beach, but where did the feldspar go?
That's the secret to this beach.
The feldspar has been removed, it's been extracted by the china clay industry, but they've been left with the quartz and it's now found its way down on to this beach.
This beach is a strip of industrial garbage?
That's right.
This beautiful beach is actually the waste product left over by the extraction of china clay from granite.
The mica and quartz that make up this unusual beach have been washed down river from the clay processing plants inland.
These huge pits are where the clay is extracted from the granite, generating a waste sand that has accumulated at Carlyon Bay.
China clay might get its name from the Chinese potters that made it famous, but one quarter of the world's china clay comes from Cornish granite.
As the rock weathers over millions of years, it softens, making this rotten granite ripe for mining.
That high pressure hose is blasting geologically rotten granite into a slurry that can be processed into china clay.
Once you have the clay, which is the mineral component it needs more processing before it becomes china clay.
These pits produce two million tonnes a year.
That's a lot of tea cups!
But this is about much more than pottery.
Do a little research and you find china clay is in lots of things.
Bizarrely, it has over 500 different commercial uses, some of them quite unexpected!
So, what exactly is china clay?
In simple terms it's rotten granite.
In fact the white material in there has a whole range of uses, everything from manufacturing paper to paint.
So, why do you need this stuff, rather than any other raw material to put it into car dash boards, or paper or paint or tooth paste or pills or whatever?
It's a hugely versatile mineral which can give gloss to paper...
Oh, the shine to paper?
It can give shine to paper, it can give impact resistance in a fender in a car.
It can be used in the electrical installation wiring systems in a dash board, so there are many, many uses.
Of course, many of us will take china clay in the form of medicine.
Why would I want to put this in some medicine?
Simply, it is an inert carrier.
It carries the other chemicals through the system.
So it's a fluid?
Just to carry it through the body, yes.
Which of the various products that I've brought along has the most china clay in it?
Well, surprisingly it is paper.
A magazine like the Radio Times would contain a third by weight of china clay.
For every one tonne of china clay extracted, there are nine tonnes of waste.
So spectacular were the mountains of waste, that they were known locally as the Cornish Alps.
In the last decade, the industry's been trying to clean up its act, by landscaping these man-made hills.
One disused china clay pit has been transformed into a tourist attraction, the Eden Project.
And a new use has been found for the waste.
It is turned into aggregates.
This means there will be no new sand washed down to Carlyon Bay so, the beach will not be replenished.
While the developers and the locals debate the future of this beach, they are actually losing it.
The china clay industry created the beach, property developers want to capitalise on it, but nature could snatch it away far faster than many people realise.
It's four years since Nick visited Carlyon Bay, but development of the site still has not begun.
I'm on a journey through Devon.
I've left Thurleston and the coast behind me and travel to Plympton to pay a visit to Dartmoor Zoo.
In October, 2006, Ben Mee and his family bought Dartmoor Zoo.
The zoo was in serious neglect and was in danger of being shut down permanently, but thankfully for the animals and for the zoo, Ben Mee and his family stepped in.
They bought it.
This created a lot of media interest at the time.
The zoo became the subject of a BBC TV series.
Ben Mee, writer and animal lover has taken on the challenge of his life.
With no previous experience, Ben, his mother and brother have sold the family home.
And bought a zoo.
Everyone tells us this is an enormous risk, friends, family, lawyers, bankers, accountants, we know it is a big risk, don't we?
But...
We do.
But it's one we want to take.
It used to be a top tourist attraction, but now, closed after council inspections, it's a zoo on death row.
If you have not got this licence renewed, the animals will have to be dispersed or shot.
Can Ben and his family save the animals and reopen the zoo?
I've caught up with Ben to see how zoo life has been treating him these past four years.
So, it's been four years on, how have things changed?
Well, this is a good example of one of the things we did earlier.
This used to be a very grim... puma enclosure with two very elderly pumas.
Where we are standing now was thick laurel, it was very dark.
We have cleared that away and increased the size of it and got a breeding pair of lynx in here, and they have actually been mating.
So we may get some little cubs.
You came with zero experience with, you know, big cats and all these animals.
How much have you learned?
I've learned a lot in a very short time and I'm still really at the bottom of a very steep learning curve.
But we established early on if we were going to do it, you have to employ proper professional keepers and a curator from whom you take your instructions.
If he advises me that I need to call the vet to treat the lion's cyst, I do.
I don't say, "It will be fine.
I'm the director."
You listen to the staff.
And in that sense we are completely in the hands of the professionals.
My job, really, is to lie awake at night, worrying about money.
Oh, no!
Everyone else, even the keepers and the people that work here has a really nice time, except me!
They are saying, "What a great place".
I'm thinking, "Is it?"
But I do hear there might be a light at the end of the tunnel.
A little birdie has told me that Hollywood might be interested in your story?
Astonishingly, when I wrote a book a while ago about the whole thing, they sold the film rights and this is fairly routine and often nothing happens.
Usually they shelve those projects and sit on them so no-one else can make them.
But I got a call the other day from Hollywood, it was late at night, on the phone, an unknown.
I'm thinking, "Do I want to take an unknown call at 10.30pm?"
It was "Hi, Ben, it's Julie from Hollywood."
"I'd just like to tell you we have a release date for Christmas 2011."
There are all these rumours of Matt Damon or Ben Stiller playing me.
It can't really be Matt Damon or Ben Stiller.
She is saying, "They are not my first choice.
"We have all the A-listers."
I'm thinking, "Yeah, yeah, sure."
Yes, probably a prank call, prank call?!
Unknown, this is probably my sister winding me up.
But they are going to set it in Hollywood.
Recreate all of these enclosures in a lot as it is cheaper than coming here and filming.
I have to go over and advise, obviously, they did say.
So, fingers crossed, Hollywood.
Yes, poorly finger crossed.
Come on, Hollywood.
Gosh, that would be amazing.
Now, can you hear that?
That is Solomon calling for his lunch.
GROWLING Shall we sort him out?
For his lunch?
Hm-mm.
OK.
Are you up for a lion feed?
I'll watch.
Oh, he's hungry!
Have I got to sacrifice myself?
Well, it can get quite dangerous.
Ben is definitely chucking me in at the deep end here.
Of course, if feeding lions does not grab you, there are plenty of other more relaxing ways to pass your time in this part of the world.
As Miriam O'Reilly discovered.
Back in the 1930s if you wanted to be in the swim, then you visited a lido.
A new wave of pleasure seekers looking for something a little more continental and stylish, flocked to these elegant new pools with their flamboyant, modern architecture.
In the 1930s, 170 lidos were built in Britain.
Now just a few, like Tinside in Plymouth, remain.
Journalist and keen swimmer Janet Smith has traced the history of the lidos from their earliest days.
The origins of the word "lido" is from the Italian and the very fashionable beach they had at Venice, known as the Lido.
So the word was adopted from there.
I'm calling them LEE-dos, you are calling them LIE-dos, which are they, are they LEE-dos or LIE-dos?
This is a very good question.
I'm sure you will hear both of them as you travel around.
A lot of people do say LIE-do and I'm one of them.
Correctly, it's LEE-do because it's Italian, but it's become anglicised.
There are other Italian words we anglicise.
Cinema is really an Italian word, but who says CHIN-ema?
So why not anglicise lido as well?
Why was it that lidos were adopted by the British?
Knowing our weather and how changeable it can be?
Funnily enough they did already exist here from the turn of the century, there were very basic open-air pools.
But in the 1930s they really came over in a big way from Germany, where they were very into open-air swimming and open-air exercise, generally.
It was a very simple way for people to enjoy, almost a holiday.
It was like a holiday destination.
Something that could be done very cheaply and very easily and by the whole family and you didn't have to travel very far to get to your nearest pool because nearly every town and city throughout the country would have its own lido.
Tinside Lido is thriving today, but back in the early '90s, it fell on hard times and was almost derelict, but when the council announced plans to demolish it, local people rallied and the pool was saved.
Tinside is now enjoyed by visitors from around the world.
This is actually the first time we've come.
My wife has a memory of this.
She used to come here as a child on holiday when her parents lived in Hampshire.
It was her regular holiday spot.
So we've come here to find it exactly, it must have been as it was before.
It was lovely to find it put to use again.
Because as a child, you know, we used to come up here most of the time.
It is even lovelier now, really, than it ever used to be.
I have never seen a pool like this before, it is beautiful.
And when I jumped in, not realising that it was a saltwater pool it was a bit of a shock!
And it was a bit cold too, but it's lovely once you get used to it!
Once you're in your swimming kit, that is a great leveller so they were really for all classes of people.
I don't think there was any great snobbery about it.
People liked to go to their lido and enjoy themselves, so all classes would very much mix together at the pool.
Whereas the indoor pools, the earlier indoor pools, there would be first and second-class swimming baths under the same roof, but that never happened at the lidos.
It was one pool for all.
No such relaxation for me.
I'm at Dartmoor Zoo and it's feeding time for the lions.
Now, Colin is luring them into the house with a little bit of food.
That will enable us to lock them into the house, go into the enclosure and we distribute the meat in as interesting places as we can think of.
That noise, feel it.
Hello, big fellow.
He is just... incredible!
God, he nearly gave me a heart attack!
Look into his eyes, they're really...
Lacking in sympathy.
Yes!
He's looking at the outside, thinking that's where food's coming.
He knows the ritual, this is all a lot of show.
That little wire...
That little bit of mesh.
That will keep that from...?
It usually holds!
Usually.
Yep!
It should be all right.
Solomon, you be a good boy, now... when I'm walking around your enclosure with lumps of meat.
Right.
We're going in.
So, what are we feeding them?
This is pony.
'Ben tells me that Josie the female lion likes to climb for her food.
They can get up this high?
Yeah.
Amazing.
You can see the claw marks on the trunks.
Look at him, he's looking at me.
I tell you what, if anything happens I'm going so far up this tree.
Although they're spoon-fed like this and have been all their lives, I think they're third generation captive-bred, they still have the basic instincts that they need in the wild.
A couple of Christmases ago, we made a zebra out of cardboard, painted it up, put bits of meat in it and stuff.
Put it down there with the lions locked in.
I thought maybe they'll be scared, seeing this huge thing.
It'd be embarrassing, cos people would be taking pictures.
We opened the hatch and it was four seconds between the hatch and the zebra.
The lioness was on the back, dragged it down.
When the kill was confirmed, Solomon swanned up and took the carcass, stood over it and bellowed for four days.
"My kill."
And she's going, "I killed it, I killed it!"
She is the real killer and he is the showman.
So if they took four seconds to get from there, all the way down there...
Yes!
He's staring at me right now from there, so he can get to me in a split second.
Yes, less than one second.
I think it's time to go.
I'm out, I'm alive!
Oh!
Amazing.
Well, when she climbed that tree, I was glad I wasn't still up there.
It's a strange place to be in there, isn't it?
Once you're in there, you realise, that's your five-minute window.
If you were in there now, they'd be eating us.
You've had the zoo three years now.
Is this why you did it - the adrenaline rush.
Walking in, seeing it, feeding them.
For me, the first time, I'm just blown away.
Well, it is a really very happy by-product of... owning it and living here.
That you get to do this.
Although I don't get to do it that much, as I'm usually stuck at a desk somewhere.
Right.
Messing about with accountants and things.
I know running a zoo is hard work, and I know it's been tough for the last couple of years for you.
Would you do it again?
I used to have an answer for that, which was, "Absolutely.
No question."
And after this winter I'm thinking...
But no, I totally would.
There's something about this place, it has its own energy, momentum.
All these animals here.
The way people react when they come and see them.
Definitely, I'd do it again, yes.
That was the most exhilarating experience I have ever had.
Just the power.
And when he bellowed you could feel it in your stomach.
That's something I'll never, ever going to forget.
Sadly it is time to leave Dartmoor Zoo and continue on my Devon journey.
When Matt Baker and Julia Bradbury visited Devon, they went to explore the picturesque Tamar Valley.
But this area isn't just famous for its landscape, there used to be a thriving mining industry here, digging out copper, tin and arsenic.
Arsenic has been used as a pesticide and an insecticide.
It's extremely poisonous, and residues have been abandoned across the county, resulting in spoil heaps like these.
It might look a little unsightly to some, but to a mountain biker, they offer the same adrenaline-pumping terrain that bikers love.
Now that used to be a problem, but thanks to a series of new trails, they can cycle in safety.
Tim, what were your major concerns about bikers biking through this terrain?
Well, we're in one of the most contaminated sites in Britain.
The mine was the biggest copper and biggest arsenic producer in the world in the mid-19th century.
This on the walls behind us here, that is arsenic, isn't it?
That is some of the remnants of arsenic.
The bikers that came here knew that if they scraped their knee on it, it would take some time to heal, so they were well aware of the dangers, but also well aware of the excitement they had on the site as well.
But I'm still seeing bikers around here.
They are still thrill-seeking?
Yes, but we've got them off the worst sites onto safer routes.
So we've built a big infrastructure so they can get in here safely, so they're organised, insured and safe.
Goodness me!
The Woodland Riders are the biggest downhill mountain bike club in the country.
They're based here in the Tamar Valley, and as you can see, these boys don't mess about!
These new downhill tracks came about through co-operation with the riders, the Tamar Valley AONB and a big chunk of Lottery funding.
So, Derek, this then is a great example of reuse of an old industrial place?
It's a fabulous old mining area, which we're now using effectively for an alternative use, which everybody's loving.
We saw the possibilities over here and had the support to make it possible here.
Three new bike tracks have been built here, dropping 500 feet in less than a mile.
So, Rowan, where do you start when you design a course like this?
We're looking for exactly this - the natural features on the hill.
Is it difficult when you're working in an Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty, are there constraints there?
It throws up a few challenges which you perhaps wouldn't have elsewhere.
If you had a normal plantation, you can pretty much do what you like, blank canvass.
But on this site, there are some archaeological constraints.
That set some boundaries for us.
When you're looking at an area like this, do you give certain routes through it, easy options?
Although this track we're on now is aimed at more advanced riders, there are still different options and lines.
So this one we're looking at here is the more expert line, because it takes more skill to ride, and there's an easier, gentler line around the back.
'Well, now I'm fully clued up about the course, 'it's time to get on my bike and put on plenty of safety gear.'
So, Rowan, we're tackling the HSD course, which means?
High Speed Descent.
Right, and how fast is that?
Wow!
Tell you what, talk about high-speed descent, you don't half get some speed up down there.
But this is your first time back here since the official opening, as the designer, it must be brilliant to see people enjoying this course.
Yeah.
You've a grin on your face.
I have!
I enjoy it, I know I'm going to, but it's good to see other people enjoying it.
Matt Baker getting to grips with some extreme mountain biking.
My journey has now taken me to Calstock.
It's a charming village near the Tamar Valley, but I can't stay long, I need to catch a ride on the Tamar Valley ferry.
I've been told that travelling on the Tamar Valley ferry is like stepping back in time.
We're heading downstream to Cotehele, it's only about a 15-minute journey and it allows me to take in the most beautiful river scenery.
The Tamar Valley is a classified Area Of Outstanding Natural Beauty.
It also forms a part of the border between Devon and Cornwall.
What a wonderful way to travel!
I've arrived so relaxed at my next destination, Cotehele National Park.
The National Park is also home to a beautiful stately home.
High above the wooded valley of the Tamar River there stands a house which has been on this site for nearly six centuries - Cotehele.
And until it was acquired by the National Trust in 1947, it had been the home of just one family, the Edgcumbes.
It's one of the jewels of the National Trust's treasure box and the job of managing it goes to Rachel Hunt who actually lives in the house.
What's it like, not just working, but living in a house like this?
Well, it's really lovely.
In any other job, you wouldn't get the chance to live somewhere like this, so it is a privilege, but a mixed blessing, you take the rough with the smooth.
If the alarm goes off in the night, then it becomes your problem.
So you're living above the shop, really?
Yes.
It doesn't look to have changed all that much for hundreds of years.
Well, it's quite deceptive, because it was actually remodelled in 1862, the butler's house back there was completely added on, so it has changed quite a lot.
What about the inside?
Some remodelling was carried out in the 1650s, but it's remained without electric lighting and only very limited electricity.
Really?
Yes.
Why is that?
Well, to install electric lighting and major electrical works would compromise the integrity of the building.
It's got a lovely character as it is, and part of the character is the gloominess.
Cotehele is just one of around 300 properties looked after by the National Trust, ranging from lighthouses to castles.
The Trust was formed in late Victorian times, but it really came into its own in 1907, with an Act Of Parliament which allowed it to keep everything it has for everyone forever.
Mark Harold has worked for the Trust for 20 years, and now oversees everything it holds in Devon and Cornwall.
How did the Trust come about?
It happened at a time when there were lots of different movements looking at the protection of places.
And it brought together three very special people - Octavia Hill, who was interested in providing breathing spaces for the poor, spaces where they could get some form of recreation, and Canon Hardwicke Rawnsley and also Robert Hunter.
Those three special people actually came together to form the basis of the National Trust.
Did the idea take off straight away?
It did, but they were involved in other things too, so the early days were quite slow, but actually collecting together a few special properties.
In fact, some of our very early attempts to protect places, like Sayes Court Garden, weren't successful, but they gave that sort of passion and that desire to protect, which really has grown and grown in the Trust that we see today.
Of course, the big thing that boosted the Trust was the act that more or less created it in 1907?
Particularly that part which actually set out our core thing, the one thing that really makes us special, and that's our ability to declare land inalienable.
And what that means, really, is that we hold things forever and they're protected forever.
So once we've declared something inalienable, we can't sell it, it can't be taken away from us, we can't mortgage it.
It really sets the Trust for that very long view ahead.
'The house here is just one of the many treasures this National Park has on offer.'
And a walk through the woodland, away from Cotehele House, leads you...to another.
Cotehele Water Mill is a restored late-18th-century working water mill.
There are only around 30 of these left in the UK today.
So I'm delighted Roger Varrow has agreed to show me around.
Can you tell me, how does it all work?
Sure, yes.
We store our grain on the floor above.
The grain comes down this chute here, and just by pulling this out, we can allow the grain into this small hopper.
And as the millstones are turning here, you can see down here, this is called the shoe, and it's being agitated backwards and forwards, and the grain is falling through there, it goes down between the millstones.
They go in an opposite direction, is that right?
It's the top stone that's actually turning.
The bed stone is the one that's stationary, it's fixed to the floor.
The grain drops in between the two and then the flour is driven around inside and goes down the chute.
And at the moment you're making plain flour here?
No, it's wholemeal flour that we produce.
OK, lovely.
What's the difference between making a plain and a wholemeal?
With a wholemeal flour, everything that's in the grain comes out in the flour.
We don't take anything out of it, so all the goodness is there.
We take wholemeal flour and then we can make white flour from it by a process of sieving.
Ah, so this is it, this is where it comes out.
Can you explain what's going on behind us?
Yes, certainly.
Behind the wall there is the water wheel.
At the bottom, there's a shaft that runs through the wall.
The water wheel is mounted on the shaft, the other side.
So the drive's coming through into the mill.
What you see in front of you here is a very old-fashioned gearbox.
The water wheel is turning quite slowly, but we need to turn the millstones much, much faster.
So there used to be so many mills around the UK, suddenly they all disappeared.
So, what happened?
At one time, there were thousands of little mills like this all over the country, but round about the 1900s the roller-mill process was introduced.
And that was a very efficient way of producing flour from wheat grain.
They were powered, firstly, by steam engines, and later, by large electric motors.
They could produce flour much more cheaply than little mills like this, using the traditional method.
The mill and the house here at Cotehele are examples of the nation's history being beautifully maintained to safeguard them for future generations.
The same, however, cannot be said of Hallsands, a fishing village on the South Devon Coast, which fell victim to the forces of nature in 1917.
So, how many houses were there originally in Hallsands?
At its height, there were 37 houses with 159 people.
Everybody, kind of, owed part of their living either directly or indirectly to the sea.
The beach had a shingle ridge which was high enough and protective enough for them to be able to leave the boats on the beach all year round.
It's entirely disappeared now.
Where we are standing, here, these were the foundations of the London Inn, the only pub in the village.
So presumably there wasn't just a sheer drop down here at that point?
No, the sand and shingle came up to the level of this rock platform.
Before the storm, there would have been a path leading up to the front of this house.
Today I can only get to it on the end of a rope.
I wonder what it must have been like on that terrible night?
On January the 26th, 1917, the wind and waves had been building up all day, until by nightfall, it was a horrendous storm.
I've got a tape here with the words of Edith Patey, who was one of the survivors of that dreadful night back in 1917.
We were counting the waves, every wave seemed to be more heavier than the last one.
And we were counting nine, and we thought this one will be a bigger one.
Then it was rolling over the rooftops and breaking over thatched roofing, the boards, you know, the rafters.
It's the very high waves that does the damage.
Then we could see the floor slipping away, the coal house slipping away, all of it going down to a huge pit.
It couldn't be repaired, beyond repair, but you have a little place as a sacred memory.
The amazing thing about that night was that nobody was killed.
In fact nobody was even seriously injured, but the village was completely ruined.
In the past, the village had had its fair share of severe weather and survived, but on this night there were other forces at work which together proved catastrophic.
Oceanographer Vince May has studied the role played by the bay's geology, in turning bad weather into disaster.
I still don't understand why Hallsands, in particular, was affected though?
Why that village out of all of the villages on the coast here?
It was the combination of high tides, strong winds and a lot of shingle removed by dredging.
The village's misfortune was its shingle beach.
Left alone, it provided the village with valuable protection against the wind and waves.
But shingle was worth a lot of money, particularly when, in 1897, Sir John Jackson's engineering company was given a licence to dredge it up and sell it.
They took out 6,000 tonnes of shingle from along here.
It sounds a huge amount.
It is probably something like 12, 15 times more than the material in the beach at the moment.
You can see, here, the old village of Hallsands and you can see that the beach goes around in front of the headland, you could have walked around in front of it, you couldn't do that today.
With British Naval power at its peak, Hallsands shingle really came into its own, a vital ingredient in a huge new building programme underway at the Devonport Naval Base just up the coast.
It was the glory days of the Empire and nobody was listening to the complaints of a few villagers.
Commander Charles Crichton knows the story better than anyone.
Just look at this here.
This is one of the docks, 700-feet long, largely built of concrete.
So this is it, this is the concrete, this is where the Hallsands shingle went?
Absolutely, there were about a million tonnes used.
Of course, the basic mix of it is sand and gravel, hence all that material was bought in.
Devonport got its big new docks, and Sir John Jackson made himself a fortune, Hallsands, however, was doomed.
100 of its inhabitants were driven out forever, their homes and livelihoods smashed.
Horseback archery is an equestrian martial art with origins going back over 2,000 years to the steppes of Eastern Europe and Asia.
Horseback archery was originally used for warfare, but it's now being rediscovered and reinvented as a sport.
It arrived in the UK just a few years ago, so I'm really excited that Hayley Bishop is going to teach me the basics.
So tell me, how long have you been doing that?
Since about 2007.
Right.
How did you get into it?
Well, I've been riding since I was about four, and I've done archery for the last seven, eight years, with a search on the internet, I found out that there was such thing as horse archery.
It's getting very popular.
It's very popular abroad, and we're promoting it in this country.
Can I have a go?
Cos I love horses.
Yes, most definitely.
But I've never...
Arched, is that what you'd call it?
Done archery.
I've never done archery in my life, but I can ride.
OK, that's brilliant.
I can ride real horses, what's this one?
This is a wooden horse, we learn on the wooden horse so that you know where the position of the neck is, and where to move your bow and what sort of positions you get into, and then you move on to the horse.
Yup, and I've got some equipment that you need to wear.
OK.
This is an arm guard.
Yeah.
I'm assuming you are right-handed?
Yes, right-handed.
No, you shoot with three, but it's just one finger that can get hurt.
Right, this is what you'll be using, this is a bow, a Korean bow.
A Korean bow?
It's the style of bow, it's nice and short.
It's brilliant for horseback archery, it doesn't hit the horse or anything.
These are three arrows, we generally only use three arrows.
So one above, two below.
I've got really long arms!
You are taking aim from where?
From this, from your chin?
No.
With horse archery you need to be slightly away from your face and you don't actually take aim, it's all instinctive.
You don't look down the arrow, it's about feel.
Oh, crikey.
OK, all right.
OK?
Well, shall I give it a go?
Right, everyone out of the back of shot...
I don't want to kill anyone!
I haven't got anywhere near the target!
Don't worry about that, the whole thing is the target.
We only use the black as something to aim at, but the whole thing is the target.
OK.
Well, I certainly feel like Robin Hood.
Do you want me to take it a tiny bit harder for you?
I can hardly do this as it is.
All right, go on.
Right, when we are riding the horse, we carry the arrows behind the bow.
I was expecting to kind of pull them out from my little backpack, like Orlando Bloom in Lord Of The Rings.
You can do it like that, but it's far easier to have it like that.
Then you get the arrow, you pull it away, you put it in the bow, and then you push it onto the string and your fingers drop down.
It's a lot trickier than it looks!
Right, well I think you are now ready for Woody, our wooden horse.
Cos it gives you a good feel of where the horse's neck is.
So you shoot from the side, not in front.
No, you shoot from the side and from the front and from the back.
So why do you shoot from all the different angles?
Actually, it's a Hungarian-style competition.
They are all from what they would have used in combat, what they found on archaeological digs, that they would have shot forwards, sidewards and backwards.
Just have to watch how much weight you put over to your right side and keep yourself fairly central.
I've been riding all my life, would that give me any benefit at all into horse archery?
It would certainly help with balance and position because you know how to ride, but it doesn't stop beginners from learning.
As long as they learn the archery safely on the ground and learn how to ride and have balance, they can start doing this from a walk.
So there is an advantage that you could get on a horse now and learn really quickly.
Whereas a beginner will take longer, but it doesn't mean that they can't do it.
But if you can't shoot, you can't shoot!
No, you definitely have to learn archery.
So here we go.
Horse - check.
Bow and arrow - check.
Archery skills - not so check.
Hayley, tell me, what are the rules?
What have I got to do?
This is a 90-metre track, and basically you've got to canter down this track, load your arrow to your bow, and take a shot at the centre target.
The centre one?
Leave that for now, we could do a front shot, a side shot and a back shot, but now, we'll do the side shot.
One step at a time.
Yes!
I'll go off and I'll try, canter down, bow, arrow, thing, side.
Got it.
Right, here we go.
Well done!
I meant to get that one(!)
I definitely meant to get that one(!)
Well done!
Centre again!
Yay!
Absolutely brilliant.
Bull's-eye!
Yeah!
I was actually aiming for the other one, but don't tell anyone!
Right, you're doing so well, why not try all three?
Positive, hold that around there...
It's the kerfuddling of all the thingies.
So I have this one already loaded...
Yep, you can have that one pre-loaded.
Yep.
And try to load the others while cantering.
Oh, I missed it!
I couldn't load them quick enough!
That was a little bit harder, that one.
You've got to learn to load without looking.
Which is, I think, you know, several years down the line, to be honest.
Oh, well done!
Yee-ha!
You hit the target, that was brilliant!
Really, really, really loved it.
Good.
But I can certainly see how many hours of hard work you've put into it, cos it's a lot more difficult than it looks.
It is quite difficult, but it's well worth it, isn't it?
It's brilliant.
It's such a rush, it really feels great when you get a bull's-eye, which I just did.
Yay!
We could do with a good British team, so you never know, we might be ringing you up!
Here we come, England!
I started the day snorkelling to find a shipwreck.
Since then, Devon's provided me with excitement...
..and adventure.
So it seems fitting that my journey should end with a new sport that blends archery with horse riding.